Register of the Benjamin Gitlow Papers, 1918-1963
Hoover Institution Archives
Benjamin Gitlow Papers,
1918-1963
67031
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (7.5 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, minutes of meetings, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to communism and socialism in the United States and Europe.
Gitlow, Benjamin, 1891-1965
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical Note
1891, Dec. 22 Born, Elizabethport, New Jersey
1909 Joined Socialist Party
1917 Elected to New York State Legislature
1919 Expelled from Socialist Party. Founding member, Communist Labor Party (later merged into Communist Party). Convicted under New York criminal syndicalism law and imprisoned
1921 Communist candidate for mayor of New York City
1922 Released from prison
1924, 1928 Communist candidate for Vice President of the U.S.
1926-1941 Member, board of directors, American Fund for Public Service (Garland Fund)
1928 Elected alternate member, Executive Committee, Communist International
1929 Elected secretary-general, Communist Party. Expelled from Communist Party. Founding member, Communist Party (Majority Group) (later known as Communist Party [Opposition])
1933 Expelled from Communist Party (Opposition)
1933-1934 Founding member and principal leader of three successive small organizations: Workers Communist League, Labor Party Association, and Organization Committee for a Revolutionary Workers Party
1934 Rejoined Socialist Party. Subsequently resigned
1939 Anti-communist witness before U.S. House Un-American Activities Committee
1940 Author, I Confess: The Truth about American Communism
1948 Author, The Whole of Their Lives: Communism in America: A Personal History and Intimate Portrayal of Its Leaders
1965, July 19 Died, Crompond, New York
Communism--Europe.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Europe.; Socialism--Europe.; Socialism--United States.; United States--Politics and government.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1932-1954. (Box 1-5)
  Scope and Contents note
  Drafts, galleys, and printed copies of speeches and writings by Benjamin Gitlow, together with letters, clippings, and other related material, arranged chronologically.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1963. (Box 5-18)
  Correspondence, minutes, reports, resolutions, statements, memoranda, notes, bulletins, leaflets, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by topic.
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE. (Envelope A)
  General note
  Two photographs of striking silk workers, Paterson, New Jersey, 1931; and 1 miscellaneous drawing.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - Some Plain Words on Communist Unity (pamphlet), Printed copy, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Testimony, U.S. House of Representatives Un-American Activities Committee, Clippings, 1939. 1939-1940 (Folder 2)
  - I Confess: The Truth about American Communism, 1940
    - Prospectus. Includes biographical sketch (Folder 3)
    - Drafts (Folder 4-9)
    - Drafts (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Drafts (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Galleys (Folder 3)
    - Reviews, 1940-1943 (Folder 4)
  - Untitled writing relating to communism in the United States, Typescript, 1940? (Folder 5)
  - Speeches, Clippings, announcements, and promotional material (including biographical sketch), 1940-1954. 1940-1954 (Folder 6)
  - Series of articles written for Il Martello, Includes "The Stalinist Racket among the Unemployed," "Bob Minor Stalin's New Errand Boy in the United States," "Hillman Delivers the Goods," "Mexican Labor at the Crossroads," "Watch Senator Nye and Wheeler" and "Stalin the Sphynx [sic]." Typescripts, Mar. 1941. (Folder 7)
  - Testimony, Rapp-Coudert Committee of New York State Legislature, Clippings, June 4, 1941. 1941 (Folder 8)
  - "Statement on the Dissolution of the Communist International," Typescript, 1943. (Folder 9)
  - "Human Side of Communism" (projected book to be written with George Hewitt), Prospectus, notes, and biographical sketch of Hewitt, 1945? (Folder 10)
  - "The Theatre's Trojan Horse," Typescript, 1948. (Folder 11)
  - The Whole of Their Lives: Communism in America: A Personal History and Intimate Portrayal of Its Leaders, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Galleys (Folder 1-4)
    - Galleys (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Reviews, Includes a letter, 1948-1953. (Folder 2)
  - "The Red Peril in Asia: How the United States in Asia Lost World War II," Prospectus and letter, 1949. 1949 (Folder 3)
  - "Communist Psychology, Tactics and Amorality," speech, American Legion National Americanism Commission Area Conference on Subversive Activities, Indianapolis, Ind., Mimeographed transcript, and clipping, Feb. 12, 1949. 1949 (Folder 4)
  - Speeches, American Legion pageant, Mosinee, Wis., Pageant consisted of mock communist coup in Mosinee with Benjamin Gitlow and Joseph Kornfeder (Joseph Zack) impersonating commissars. Typescript, holograph, program, clipping, leaflets, and memorabilia, Apr. 30-May 1, 1950. 1950 (Folder 5)
  - Testimony, U.S. Department of Justice hearing, Washington, D.C., Prepared commentary on exhibits, summary of previous testimony, and letters, Apr. 23, 1951. 1951 (Folder 6)
  - Letter to the editor, Peekskill (N.Y.) Evening Star, (date written). Relates to Israel Goldstein. Typescript, Sept. 23, 1953 (Folder 7)
  - "Behind the Red Curtain on Broadway," Prospectus (Folder 8)
  - "An Open Letter to Communists and Communist Sympathizers," Statement to publicize the book by Victor Kravchenko, I Chose Freedom. Typescript, galley, and letter by Eugene Lyons (Folder 9)
  - Series of articles on Soviet espionage, Includes "Inside the American Communist Spy System," "Seduction Is Their Racket," "I Defied Stalin," " 'Inside' the Commies," "They Can Get You Too!" "How the NKVD Uses the Unions for Industrial and Scientific Expionage," "Sex a Weapon of the NKVD," "The Carlo Tresca Murder," "The Poyntz Mystery," "Inside the Communist Spy Ring in America," and "Do You Want to Be a Communist?" Prospectuses, drafts, and notes (Folder 10)
- SUBJECT FILE
  - American China Policy Association.Correspondence (almost entirely mimeographed open letters by Alfred Kohlberg), memoranda, press releases, and printed matter circulated by the American China Policy Association, 1945-1951 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - American China Policy Association. Correspondence (almost entirely mimeographed open letters by Alfred Kohlberg), memoranda, press releases, and printed matter circulated by the American China Policy Association, 1952-1960 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - American Fund for Public Service
    - General. Memoranda, statistics, notes, clipping, and correspondence with Roger N. Baldwin, Robert W. Dunn, Max Eastman, Sherwood Eddy, Morris L. Ernst, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Charles Garland, Jay Lovestone, Scott Nearing, C. E. Ruthenberg, Norman Thomas, Harry F. Ward, Bertram D. Wolfe and others, 1925-1941 (Folder 3)
    - Funding of Brookwood Labor College. Statements, memoranda, statistics, and correspondence with Roger N. Baldwin, Robert W. Dunn, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, J. C. Kennedy, A. J. Muste, Tucker P. Smith and others, 1926-1938 (Folder 4)
    - Funding of Vanguard Press. Report, memorandum, miscellany, and correspondence with Jacob Baker, Roger N. Baldwin and others, 1926-1939 (Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1925-1941 (Folder 6)
    - Reports, Includes audits, 1923-1941. (Folder 7)
  - American Jewish League against Communism (Box 7)
    - General. Constitution, minutes, memoranda, statements, press releases, notes, miscellany, and correspondence with Alfred Kohlberg, Benjamin Schultz and others, 1948-1959 (Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1946-1953 (Folder 2)
  - American Labor Party. Clippings, and leaflets, 1939-1954 (Folder 3)
  - American League against War and Fascism. Study by Hillman M. Bishop entitled "The American League against War and Fascism: A Study in Communist Tactics," bulletin, and leaflets, 1934-1937 (Folder 4)
  - American Radio Telegraphists Association. Bulletins, 1938-1939 (Folder 5)
  - Asia. Printed articles, and clippings, 1942-1956 (Folder 6)
  - China. Bulletin, printed articles, and clippings, 1930-1958 (Folder 7)
  - Communism
    - General. Three studies: "The Communist International Conspiracy" by Julius N. Cahn, and "The Communist Conspiracy in Canada" and "The Nature of the Communist Movement", both anonymous; leaflets, correspondence, and miscellany, 1938-1959 (Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1938-1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Communism and mass media. Speech by Eleanor A. Buchanan, entitled "Will You Help Me?" serial issues, printed articles, clippings, leaflets, bulletins, notes, and letters, 1940-1956 (Folder 2)
  - Communism in education
    - General. Legal briefs relating to faculty members at the University of Washington, serial issues, leaflets, reports, and letter, 1948-1954 (Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1938-1955 (Folder 4)
  - Communist League of Struggle. Serial issue, leaflets, article by Albert Weisbord entitled "The Right Wing CPUSA," and letter by Weisbord, 1931-1934 (Folder 5)
  - Communist Party, U.S.A.
    - General. Statement by Harry M. Winitsky, speech by Erle Cocke, Jr., legal briefs and decision, memoranda, bulletin, leaflets, and correspondence with Max Bedacht, Milton Gibbs, John Reed and others, 1919-1951 (Folder 6)
    - Clippings, 1921-1956 (Folder 7)
    - Miscellany. Receipts and memorabilia, 1923-1926 (Folder 8)
    - Notes, Evidently used in the writing of I Confess and/or The Whole of Their Lives (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Printed articles, 1939-1953 (Folder 3)
    - Serial issues, 1933-1956 (Folder 4)
  - Communist Party, U.S.A. (Opposition)
    - Correspondence with Roger N. Baldwin, David Benjamin, Hal Boyer, Louis Francis Budenz, Harry Conner, Will Herberg, Jay Lovestone, Bert Miller (Benjamin Mandel), Tom Mooney, Tom O'Flaherty, Arne Swabeck, Frank Vrataric, Edward Wright, Herbert Zam and others, 1929-1933 (Folder 5-6)
    - Leaflets, 1930-1933 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1930-1932 (Folder 2)
    - Miscellany. Receipts, tickets, membership cards, notes, and lists, 1930-1932 (Folder 3)
    - Printed matter. Legal brief, serial issues, and clippings, 1930-1953 (Folder 4)
    - Resolutions, reports, and statements, 1930-1933 (Folder 5-6)
  - Council against Communist Aggression. Mimeographed material circulated by the Council against Communist Aggression, including statements, resolutions, speeches, and letters by Arthur G. McDowell, 1952-1957 (Folder 7)
  - Council against Communist Aggression. Mimeographed material circulated by the Council against Communist Aggression, including statements, resolutions, speeches, and letters by Arthur G. McDowell, 1958-1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Espionage, Russian. Study by J. Anthony Marcus entitled "How the Soviets Steal Our Industrial Secrets," printed articles, and clippings, 1941-1957 (Folder 2)
  - Europe. Clippings, printed articles, serial issues, and form letters, 1933-1959 (Folder 3-4)
  - Fourth International. Position papers by Albert Goldman, internal bulletin, leaflets, press release, printed article, and clippings, 1933-1959 (Folder 5)
  - Germany. Clippings, and printed articles, 1941-1954 (Folder 6)
  - International Bureau for Revolutionary Socialist Unity. Bulletins, statements, press releases, leaflets, and letters by Fenner Brockway, 1935-1938 (Folder 7)
  - International Bureau of Revolutionary Youth Organizations. Bulletins, 1934-1935 (Folder 8)
  - Labor and Socialist Press Service. Bulletins, 1934-1935 (Folder 9)
  - Labor Party Association (Box 12)
    - Correspondence with Lazar Becker, Alfred M. Bingham, V. F. Calverton, James P. Cannon, Harry Conner, B. J. Field, Sam Gampel, Francis A. Henson, Norman W. Lermond, A. J. Muste, Upton Sinclair, Herbert Solow, Allen Stiller, Albert Weisbord, Scott Wilkins, Herbert Zam and others, 1933-1934 (Folder 1-2)
    - Minutes, 1933-1934 (Folder 3)
    - Miscellany. Financial records, receipts, notes, serial issue, and leaflets, 1933-1934 (Folder 4)
    - Resolutions, reports, and statements, 1933-1934 (Folder 5)
  - Latin America. Clippings, printed articles, and form letter, 1941-1956 (Folder 6)
  - Loyalty-security program, 1947-
    - General. "Report of the President's Temporary Commission on Employee Loyalty"; three studies: "Know Your Enemy" by Carl Baarslag, and "The Communist Underground" and "The Lincoln-Petkov Academy and the National Academy Organizations," both anonymous; interview of Benjamin Mandel; speech by William E. Jenner; conference program, memoranda, bulletins, newsletters, and leaflets, 1941-1954 (Folder 7-8)
    - Clippings, 1940-1962 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Murphy, J. T. Clippings, 1932 (Folder 3)
  - Near East. Clippings, and printed articles, 1947-1959 (Folder 4)
  - Paterson, N. J. - Silk Workers' Strike, 1931
    - General. Reports, resolutions, memoranda, notes, bulletin, press releases, lists, miscellany, and correspondence, 1931 (Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1931 (Folder 6-7)
    - Clippings, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 1-4)
    - Financial records, 1931 (Folder 5)
    - Leaflets, 1931 (Folder 6)
  - Russia (Box 15)
    - General. Anonymous study entitled "Concerning Stalin's Intentions"; "The Terror in Stalin's Russia: An Open Letter to Upton Sinclair" by Eugene Lyons; leaflets, notes, telegram, and a letter by J. N. Golos, 1938-1953 (Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1933-1956 (Folder 2-4)
    - Printed articles, 1938-1959 (Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party
    - Clippings, 1919-1934 (Folder 6)
    - Convention, New York City, Transcript of proceedings, 1928. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Jack Altman, Louis P. Lochner, Clarence Senior and others, 1918-1953 (Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1935-1936 (Folder 3)
    - Printed matter. Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issue, and printed article, 1918-1938 (Folder 4)
    - Resolutions, reports, and statements, 1934-1940 (Folder 5)
  - Sverges Socialistiska Partiet. Bulletin, 1934 (Folder 6)
  - Tenney, Jack B. Newspaper columns by Tenney, and letter by Tenney, 1951-1952 (Folder 7)
  - Trade-unions. Leaflets, clippings, printed articles, and miscellany, 1931-1956 (Folder 8-9)
  - Trade-unions. Leaflets, clippings, printed articles, and miscellany (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Trade-unions and communism. Leaflets, clippings, and printed articles, 1931-1958 (Folder 2)
  - Tresca, Carlo. Leaflets, press release, clipping, and letter, 1939-1948 (Folder 3)
  - Unemployed. Statements, and leaflets (Folder 4)
  - United Council of Working Women. Typed copy of pamphlet by Kate Gitlow entitled Women in Politics, speech by Kate Gitlow, resolutions, reports, statements, minutes, announcements, notes, and correspondence with John J. Ballam, Kate Gitlow, Bert Miller (Benjamin Mandel) and others, 1926-1929 (Folder 5-6)
  - United States
    - General. Article by Benjamin Mandel entitled "After Roosevelt - What?", newsletter, press releases, leaflets, miscellany, and letters, 1932-1934 (Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1928-1963 (Folder 8-9)
    - Clippings, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Printed articles, 1938-1959 (Folder 2)
  - Workers Defense League. Press releases, leaflets, and form letters, 1941-1942 (Folder 3)
  - Workers' Health Bureau of America. Pamphlets, leaflets, and conference proceedings, 1924-1927 (Folder 4)
  - World politics
    - Clippings, 1939-1956 (Folder 5-6)
    - Printed articles, 1939-1959 (Folder 7)
  - Yugoslavia. Clippings, and printed articles, 1945-1956 (Folder 8)
  - Zack, Joseph. Press release, clippings, and letter by Zack, 1938-1944 (Folder 9)